'Theme and variations' is one of those forms that
الفكرة والتغيير هي احد تلك الاشكال التي
require a certain kind of intellectual activity,
تتطلب نوع معين من النشاط الذهني
because you are always comparing the variation
وذلك لأنك دائما ما تقارن التغيير
with the theme that you hold in your mind.
مع المواضيع التي في ذاكرتك
You might say that the theme is nature
ربما تقول في داخلك تلك المواضيع طبيعية
and everything that follows is a variation on the subject.
وكل شيء يتبعه ماهو الا تغيير في الموضوع
I was asked, I guess about six years ago,
ولقد طلب مني , اعتقد قبل ست سنوات
to do a series of paintings
أن اعمل مجموعة من اللوحات الفنية
that in some way would celebrate the birth of Piero della Francesca.
وذلك بطريقة ما نحتفل بمولد بيرو ديلا فرانشيسكا
And it was very difficult for me to imagine
وكان من الصعب جدا أن أتخيل
how to paint pictures that were based on Piero
كيف لي أن أرسم صورة تكون مرتكزة على رسومات بيرو
until I realized that I could look at Piero as nature --
والى أن ادركت , انني أستطيع أن انظر الى بيرو على انه مشهد طبيعي
that I would have the same attitude towards looking at Piero della Francesca
حاوت ان احصل على نفس الاحساس حين النظر الى بيرو ديلا فرانشيسكا
as I would if I were looking out a window at a tree.
كما لو انني انظر الى شجرة من النافذة
And that was enormously liberating to me.
وكان ذلك تصرفاً محررا لي ..
Perhaps it's not a very insightful observation,
وربما لم يكن تصرفاً يُلحظ بسهولة
but that really started me on a path to be able to do a kind of theme and variations
ولكنه في الحقيقة مكنني من ان ابدأ الطريق في الرسم .. بعدة أوجه
based on a work by Piero,
وتبعاً لعمل بدأه بيرو
in this case that remarkable painting that's in the Uffizi, "The Duke of Montefeltro,"
في هذه الحالة رسمت " دوق مونتيفيلتو "
who faces his consort, Battista.
الذي هو وجهه أمام وجه باتيستا
Once I realized that I could take some liberties with the subject,
ومن ثم ادركت انني يمكنني ان اقوم بعدة اوجه لهذا العمل
I did the following series of drawings.
وقمت بعمل عدة رسومات
That's the real Piero della Francesca --
هذا هو بيرو ديلا فرانشيسكا
one of the greatest portraits in human history.
هذه واحدة من افضل الرسومات في التاريخ البشري
And these, I'll just show these without comment.
وهذه .. سوف اعرض هذه بدون تعليقات
It's just a series of variations on the head of the Duke of Montefeltro,
انها صور عدة لوجه دوق مونتيفيلترو
who's a great, great figure in the Renaissance,
وهو شخص مهم جداً في عصر النهضة
and probably the basis for Machiavelli's "The Prince."
ومن المحتمل هو الأساس لميكافيلي "الأمير".
He apparently lost an eye in battle,
وهو قد فقد عيناً في احدا المعارك
which is why he is always shown in profile.
ولهذا السبب يظهر هكذا في كل الصور
And this is Battista.
وهذه هي باتيستا
And then I decided I could move them around a little bit --
ومن ثم قررت ان احرك الامور قليلاً
so that for the first time in history, they're facing the same direction.
وها هما لاول مرة في التاريخ ينظران الى نفس الوجهة
Whoops! Passed each other.
هااا ! .. يواجهان بعضهما البعض
And then a visitor from another painting by Piero,
وها هو قادم جديد من لوحة أخرى لبيرو
this is from "The Resurrection of Christ" --
انها لوحة " بعث المسيح "
as though the cast had just gotten of the set to have a chat.
وربما ظنوا انهم يمكنهم الشروع في محادثة ما
And now, four large panels:
وها هي الزوايا الاربعة
this is upper left;
العلوية اليسرى
upper right;
العلوية اليمنى
lower left;
السفلى اليسرى
lower right.
السفلى اليمنى
Incidentally, I've never understood the conflict between abstraction and naturalism.
وبالمناسبة ، لم أفهم مطلقا الصراع بين التجريد والمذهب الطبيعي
Since all paintings are inherently abstract to begin with
على اعتبار كل اللوحات تكون مجردة حين البدء فيها
there doesn't seem to be an argument there.
ولا يبدو هناك اشكال لدي في هذه الجزئية
On another subject --
لننتقل الى موضوع آخر
(Laughter) --
(ضحك)
I was driving in the country one day with my wife,
كنت اقود ذات يوم مع زوجتي في الريف
and I saw this sign,
ومن ثم رأيتُ هذه اللوحة
and I said, "That is a fabulous piece of design."
وقلت في نفسي " انه تصميم مبدع "
And she said, "What are you talking about?"
فردت علي زوجتي " عن ماذا تتحدث "
I said, "Well, it's so persuasive,
قلت " انها مقنعة
because the purpose of that sign is to get you into the garage,
لان الهدف من الاعلان هو ان تذهب الى الكراج
and since most people are so suspicious of garages,
ولان معظم الاشخاص يحتاطون من الكراج
and know that they're going to be ripped off,
لانهم يعلمون انهم سوف يسلبون هناك
they use the word 'reliable.'
فقد استخدموا عبارة " يمكن الوثوق به "
But everybody says they're reliable.
ولكن الجميع يقول عن انفسهم " انه يمكن الوثوق بهم "
But, reliable Dutchman" --
ولكن هولندي يمكن الوثوق به
(Laughter) --
(ضحك)
"Fantastic!"
فهذه سابقة رائعة
Because as soon as you hear the word Dutchman --
لانه ما ان تسمع عبارة هولندي
which is an archaic word, nobody calls Dutch people "Dutchmen" anymore --
والتي هي عبارة تاريخية لانه لا احد يصف اليوم الهولنديون ب " داتش بيبول "
but as soon as you hear Dutchman,
ولكن ما ان تسمع عبارة الهولندي
you get this picture of the kid with his finger in the dike,
حتى يخرج الى بالك مشهد الطفل عند السد
preventing the thing from falling and flooding Holland, and so on.
يحاول ان يمنع الفيضان من اجيتاح هولندا
And so the entire issue is detoxified by the use of "Dutchman."
وهذه الصورة تمثل قضية هولندا على الدوام
Now, if you think I'm exaggerating at all in this,
والان ان اعتقدتم انني ابالغ في هذا
all you have to do is substitute something else, like "Indonesian."
كل ما عليكم القيام به هو استبدال كلمة الهولندي بالاندونيسي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Or even "French."
او الفرنسي
Now, "Swiss" works, but you know it's going to cost a lot of money.
ربما السويسري قد يكون مقبولا ولكن هذا سيكلفك الكثير من المال
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'm going to take you quickly through the actual process of doing a poster.
سوف ااخذكم في رحلة عن كيفية القيام بصنع بوستر
I do a lot of work for the School of Visual Arts, where I teach,
لقد قمت بالكثير من الاعمال في مدرسة الفنون الجميلة حيث اقوم بالتدريس
and the director of this school -- a remarkable man named Silas Rhodes --
ومدير الكلية هو شخص مميز اسمه سيلاس روديس
often gives you a piece of text and he says, "Do something with this."
وهو عادة يعطيني جمل يقول لي " قم بشيء حيال هذه "
And so he did.
وعادة اخرج ببعض الاشياء
And this was the text -- "In words as fashion the same rule will hold/
وكانت هذه هي العبارة " في الكلمات مثل الموضة هناك الكثير ليقال
Alike fantastic if too new or old/
شيء مثير جديد او قديم
Be not the first by whom the new are tried/
ربما قام به احد من ذي قبل
Nor yet the last to lay the old aside."
ولكنه لم يصمد واليوم يعاد من جديد "
I could make nothing of that.
لم اكن ادري مالذي يمكنني القيام به حيال هذا
And I really struggled with this one.
في الحقيقة عانيت كثيراً بهذا
And the first thing I did, which was sort of in the absence of another idea,
واول شيء خطر ببالي هو ان استخدم كلمات واضحة واخرة لا
was say I'll sort of write it out and make some words big,
اي ان اقوم بكتابة كلمات بخط كبير
and I'll have some kind of design on the back somehow,
ومن اثم اصمم اللوحة على ان تندرج البقية في الخلف
and I was hoping -- as one often does -- to stumble into something.
وكنت اتمنى .. كما الكثير .. ان يفيد الامر
So I took another crack at it --
ولكن من ثم استخدم طريقة اخرى .. حطمت الكلمات
you've got to keep it moving --
ومن ثم استمريت بالمحاولة
and I Xeroxed some words on pieces of colored paper
وقد قمت بقصقصة كلمات بواسطة اوراق ملونة
and I pasted them down on an ugly board.
والصقتها على هذا اللوح القبيح
I thought that something would come out of it,
ومن ثم خطر ببالي القيام بشيء آخر ..
like "Words rule fantastic new old first last Pope"
مثل " الكلمات تحكم العالم الحديث القديم الاول الآخر بوب "
because it's by Alexander Pope,
لان الكلمات في الاساس هي ل ألكسندر بوب
but I sort of made a mess out of it,
ولكن في الحقيقة اختلط علي الامر
and then I thought I'd repeat it in some way so it was legible.
ومن فكرت بان اعيد الامر بصورة منطقية اكثر
So, it was going nowhere.
ولكن لم اصل الى نتيجة
Sometimes, in the middle of a resistant problem,
بعض الاحيان في خضم حدوث المشكلة
I write down things that I know about it.
اكتب بعض الاشياء التي اعرفها عنها - المشكلة -
But you can see the beginning of an idea there,
ويمكنكم ان تروا بداية حل المشكلة هنا
because you can see the word "new" emerging from the "old."
كيف ان عبارة " جديد " تخرج من صلب عبارة " قديم "
That's what happens.
هذا ما حدث
There's a relationship between the old and the new;
هناك علاقة بين القديم والجديد
the new emerges from the context of the old.
لان الجديد يخرج من القديم
And then I did some variations of it,
ومن ثم قمت بعدة اوجه لذلك الامر
but it still wasn't coalescing graphically at all.
ولكنه مازال نوعاً من ائتلاف تصويري عام
I had this other version which had something interesting about it
وكان لدي هذا الاصدار ..والذي ظننت انه ممثير للاهتمام
in terms of being able to put it together in your mind from clues.
لانه قادر على ان يدفع الدماغ للبحث عن الآثار
The W was clearly a W, the N was clearly an N,
فالحرف " W " هو فعلاً " W " و " N " هو فعلاً " N "
even though they were very fragmentary
حتى لو كانت الكلمات مجزأة
and there wasn't a lot of information in it.
ولم يكن هناك الكثير من المعلومات
Then I got the words "new" and "old"
ونوعا ما عدت الى كلمة قديم وجديد
and now I had regressed back to a point where there seemed to be no return.
وكنت الان قد تجاوزت نقطة العودة على ما يبدو
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I was really desperate at this point.
في هذه المرحلة اصبت بالاحباط حقاً
And so, I do something I'm truthfully ashamed of,
وقمت بشيء .. حقاً خجلت منه
which is that I took two drawings I had made for another purpose
فاخذت رسمتين كنت قد رسمتهما من ذي قبل
and I put them together.
ووضعتهما سوية
It says "dreams" at the top.
مكتوب عليها الاحلام في الاعلى
And I was going to do a thing, I say, "Well, change the copy.
وكنت على وشك القيام بأمر .. فقلت " حسناً .. لاغير النسخة
Let it say something about dreams, and come to SVA
دعني اجل البوستر يخبر شيئاً عن الاحلام
and you'll sort of fulfill your dreams."
ومن ثم اضيف شيئاً يعبر عن تحقيق الاحلام "
But, to my credit,
ويجب ان اذكر
I was so embarrassed about doing that
انني كنت محرجاً لانني قمت بذلك
that I never submitted this sketch.
لدرجة انني لم اقدم هذا الاصدار
And, finally, I arrived at the following solution.
وفي النهاية وصلت الى هذا الحل
Now, it doesn't look terribly interesting,
والان .. هذا الاصدار لا يبدو مثيرأً للاهتمام
but it does have something
ولكنه فيه شيء مميز
that distinguishes it from a lot of other posters.
وهذا يميزه عن كثير من الاصدارات السابقة
For one thing, it transgresses the idea of what a poster's supposed to be,
بداية انه يتعد فكرة البوستر وما يجب ان ينص عليه
which is to be understood and seen immediately, and not explained.
وهو مفهوم على الفور .. ولا يحتاج للشرح
I remember hearing all of you in the graphic arts --
انا اذكر مقولة في الفنون الجميلة كانت تقول
"If you have to explain it, it ain't working."
البوستر الذي يحتاج للشرح .. ليس ببوستراً
And one day I woke up and I said, "Well, suppose that's not true?"
وذات يوم استيقظت .. وقلت في نفسي .. ماذا لو كانت تلك العبارة خاطئة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So here's what it says in my explanation at the bottom left.
وهذا ما كتبته في تفسيري في اسفل الصورة من الطرف الايسر
It says, "Thoughts: This poem is impossible.
قلت " الافكار : الشعر هو شيء مستحيل "
Silas usually has a better touch with his choice of quotations.
سيلاس لديه عادة لمسة اجمل في اختيارات الاقتباسات
This one generates no imagery at all."
وهذه ليست تخيليلة على الاطلاق "
I am now exposing myself to my audience, right?
انا الان اكشف نفسي امام الحضور . اليس كذلك ؟
Which is something you never want to do professionally.
وهو شيء لا يقوم به المحترفون
"Maybe the words can make the image without anything else happening.
" ربما الكلمات يمكنها ان تغير الصورة بدون ان تتغير هي ذاتها "
What's the heart of this poem?
وما هو معنى هذه القصيدة
Don't be trendy if you want to be serious.
لا تكن متساهلاً حين الجدية
Is doing the poster this way trendy in itself?
ان القيام بصنع هذا البوستر بهذه الشاكلة هو التساهل بعينه
I guess one could reduce the idea further
اعتقد انه كان بالامكان تقليل عرض الفكرة اكثر
by suggesting that the new emerges behind and through the old,
عن طريق وضع كلمة الجديد وهي تخرج من كلمة القديم
like this."
مثل هذه ..
And then I show you a little drawing --
سوف اريكم رسمة بسيطة
you see, you remember that old thing I discarded?
اترون .. هل تذكرون الصورة القديمة التي تخليت عنها
Well, I found a way to use it.
حسناً . . لقد وجدت طريقة لاستخدامها
So, there's that little alternative over there,
هناك بديل قائم هنا على ما يبدو
and I say, "Not bad," -- criticizing myself --
واقول " انه ليس سيئاً - انقد نفسي هنا
"but more didactic than visual.
ولكني يبدو تلقيني .. اكثر منه بصري
Maybe what wants to be said is that old and the new are locked in a dialectical embrace,
ربما ما يمكن قوله هنا ان القديم والجديد محصوران في مسميات تلقينية
a kind of dance where each defines the other."
انها نوع من التواصل الذي يجعل كل كلمة تتوضح بالكلمة الاخرى
And then more self-questioning -- "Am I being simple-minded?
ومن ثم طرحت على نفسي تساؤلا .. هل انا بسيط التفكير بهذا التصرف
Is this the kind of simple that looks obvious, or the kind that looks profound?
هل هذه البساطة فعلا كما هي تبدو .. ام انها أصيلة جداً
There's a significant difference.
هناك اختلاف كبير
This could be embarrassing.
ربما يمكن تسمية ذلك " بالأمر المحرج "
Actually, I realize fear of embarrassment drives me as much as any ambition.
في الحقيقة .. ادركت ان الخوف من الاحراج يدفعني كما الطموح
Do you think this sort of thing could really attract a student to the school?"
هل تظنوا ان هذا النوع من الحديث يمكن ان يدفع شخصاً للتعلم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Well, I think there are two fresh things here -- two fresh things.
اعتقد ان هناك امرين جديدين هنا ..
One is the sort of willingness to expose myself to a critical audience,
الاول هو الرغبة في ان اعرض نفسي على الجمهور الناقد
and not to suggest that I am confident about what I'm doing.
دون ان ادعي انني واثق مما اقوم به
And as you know, you have to have a front.
وكما تعلمون .. يجب ان يكون لديك جبهة
I mean -- you've got to be confident;
اقصد يجب ان تملك الثقة
if you don't believe in your work, who else is going to believe in it?
ان لم تؤمن بعملك من سيؤمن به
So that's one thing,
هذا هو الامر الاول
to introduce the idea of doubt into graphics.
لعرض فكرة فيها شك " تصويري "
That can be a big contribution.
ان هذا يمكن ان يكون مساهمة كبيرة -التشكيك في عمله-
The other thing is to actually give you two solutions for the price of one;
الامر الثاني يعطيك حلين من اجل مشكلة واحدة
you get the big one
لديك الحل الاكبر ..
and if you don't like that, how about the little one?
وان لم يعجبك .. لديك الحل الاصغر
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And that too is a relatively new idea.
وهذه أيضا فكرة جديدة نسبية
And here's just a series of experiments
وهناك الكثير من التجارب
where I ask the question of -- does a poster have to be square?
حيث اسئل نفسي .. هل يجب ان يكون البوستر مربعاً
Now, this is a little illusion.
الآن .. هذا خداع بصري .. نوعا ما
That poster is not folded.
ان البوستر ليس مطوياً
It's not folded, that's a photograph
انه ليس مطوياً .. انها صورة
and it's cut on the diagonal.
وهو مقطوع بصورة قطرية
Same cheap trick in the upper left-hand corner.
نفس الامر في الزاوية العليا اليسرى
And here,
وهنا
a very peculiar poster because,
هذا بوستر مميز
simply because of using the isometric perspective in the computer,
لانه ببساطة يستخدم النظام الايزومتري في الكمبيوتر
it won't sit still in the space.
انه لا يثبت
At times, it seems to be wider at the back than the front,
في بعض الاوقات يبدو عريضاً من الخلف اكثر منه من الامام
and then it shifts.
انه يتغير
And if you sit here long enough, it'll float off the page into the audience.
وان كنت جالساً لفترة طويلة .. سوف تلاحظ انه يطوف على الصفحة تجاه المشاهد
But, we don't have time.
ولكن نحن لا نملك الوقت لذلك
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then an experiment --
وهنا تجربة ..
a little bit about the nature of perspective,
عن مفهوم الطبيعة
where the outside shape is determined by the peculiarity of perspective,
حيث يبدو الشكل الخارجي محدد بواسطة منظور خصوصي
but the shape of the bottle -- which is identical to the outside shape --
ولكن الشكل في العبوة .. يبدو متطابقاً لما هو في الخارج
is seen frontally.
ويرى من الجهة الامامية
And another piece for the art directors' club
والقطعة الاخرى .. لنادي المخرجين الفنيين
is "Anna Rees" casting long shadows.
انها آنا ريز تقدم ظلالا طويلة
This is another poster from the School of Visual Arts.
انه ليس بوستراً من مدرسة الفنون الجميلة
There were 10 artists invited to participate in it,
كان هناك 10 فنانين مدعوين للتنافس على تصميمه
and it was one of those things where it was extremely competitive
وكان واحد من الاشياء الاكثر تنافسية على الاطلاق
and I didn't want to be embarrassed,
ولم اكن اريد ان اُحرج
so I worked very hard on this.
فعملت عليه مطولاً وبكل جديه
The idea was -- and it was a brilliant idea --
كانت الفكرة .. وهي فكرة رائعة
was to have 10 posters distributed throughout the city's subway system
ان يكون هناك 10 بوسترات موزعة في مترو الانفاق في المدينة
so every time you got on the subway you'd be passing a different poster,
حيث كلما دخلت محطة ما ستجد بوسترا مختلفاً
all of which had a different idea of what art is.
وكلها تتحدث عن نفس الفكرة ولكن بلمسة فنية مختلفة
But I was absolutely stuck on the idea of "art is"
ولكن كنت متعلقاً بفكرة " الفن هو "
and trying to determine what art was.
وكنت احاول ان اعرّف الفن
But then I gave up and I said, "Well, art is whatever."
ولكن استسلمت وقلت لنفسي " الفن هو "مهما يكن.. "
And as soon as I said that,
وما ان قلت هذا
I discovered that the word "hat" was hidden in the word "whatever,"
حتى اكتشفت ان كلمة " قبعة " كانت مختبئة بين كلمة " مهما يكن " W"HAT"EVER
and that led me to the inevitable conclusion.
وبالنسبة لي كان هذا الخيط لاكتشاف مميز
But then again, it's on my list of didactic posters.
ولكن البوستر كان له غاية معينة
My intent is to have a literary accompaniment that explains the poster,
وكانت نيتي ان اجد بصورة ما شيء يشرح البوستر بصورة خفية
in case you don't get it.
في حال لم يستطع القارىء فهمه مباشرة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now this says, "Note to the viewer:
هذه تقول " ملاحظة للمشاهد ..
I thought I might use a visual cliche of our time -- Magritte's everyman --
قلت لنفسي ربما استطيع استخدام شيء مبتذل من عالمنا .. مارغريت كل شخص ..
to express the idea that art is mystery, continuity and history.
لكي اعبر عن ان الفن هو غموض واستمرار وتاريخ
I'm also convinced that, in an age of computer manipulation,
ولكني مقتنع ان هذا العصر هو عصر الرسم بالحاسوب
surrealism has become banal,
والسوريالية لم تعد سوى .. ابتذال
a shadow of its former self.
انها مجرد انعكاس لنفسها
The phrase 'Art is whatever'
ان العبارة " الفن هو مهما يكن "
expresses the current inclusiveness that surrounds art-making --
تعبر عن الشمولية الحالية المحيطة بصناعة الفن
a sort of 'it ain't what you do, it's the way that you do it' notion.
والامر بات اليوم كما القول الشهير " لا يهم ما تقوم به .. بل كيف تقوم به "
The shadow of Magritte falls across the central part of the poster
وظل مارجريت هنا يطل على جميع اجزاء البوستر
a poetic event that occurs as the shadow man isolates the word 'hat,'
انه حدث شعري .. يحدث في ظل الرجال المعزولين داخل كلمة " قبعة "
hidden in the word 'whatever.'
والتي هي بالاساس مختبئة داخل كلمة " مهما يكن "
The four hats shown in the poster suggests how art might be defined:
القبعة الامامية .. في البوستر .. توضح كيف يمكن ان يعرف الفن
as a thing itself, the worth of the thing, the shadow of the thing,
كشيء منفرد .. يستحق الاهتمام .. ظل شيء آخر
and the shape of the thing.
و ممثلاً لشيء ما
Whatever."
" مهما يكن "
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
OK.
حسناً
And the one that I did not submit,
ان البوستر الذي لم أقم بتقديمه
which I still like,
ولكني مازلت احبه
I wanted to use the same phrase.
وانا اريد ان استخدم نفس العبارة
There were wonderful experiments by Bruno Munari
التي حددت تلك التجربة الرائعة من قبل برونو موناري
on letterforms some years ago --
حيث وضع احرف منذ عدة سنوات
sort of, see how far you could go and still be able to read them.
وكان يريد من الناس ان تبتعد وتحاول قرآتها .. على شاكلتها الجديدة ..
And that idea stuck in my head.
وهذه الفكرة علقت في رأسي ..
But then I took the pieces that I had taken off and put them at the bottom.
ولكن نظرت مرة اخرى الى اللوحات التي قمت بها .. ومن ثم اخذتها .. ووضعتها في الأسفل
And, of course those are the remains, and they're so labeled.
وحتماً تلك هي البقايا .. كلوحات مميزة
But what really happens is that you read it as:
ولكن ما حدث هو ان اللوحة يجب ان تقراً.. على النحو التالي
"Art is whatever remains."
" الفن .. هو كل ما تبقى "
Thank you.
شكرأً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)